Hello and welcome to BB Linköping's large lecture "to give birth".
You are all here to listen, because you have one thing in common:
That you are expecting children.
First, second, third or even the fourth child.
What do we know.
This lecture replaces the actual lecture
we have, normally, a few times each semester,
Up on the US in Linköping.
Since we have a pandemic, we can use this agent.
We will not go into anything around the coronary restrictions
Because they change often, sometimes from day to day.
We may refer to the region's guidelines and the Public Health Authority.
My name is Lina Broberg and I work as a midwife at the birth in Linköping.
My name is Caroline Lorentzon.
I also work at the birth and BB.
Today's agenda you see here:
We were going to tell you how we work at the birth
Who works with us and how we work together.
We will also talk about how you can prepare for your birth.
And what happens when you come to us at birth.
We go through the different stages of the delivery.
The focus will be on the normal delivery process.
But we will also talk a little about when the process deviates from normal.
At the end we talk about pain and pain relief,
Both non -medical and medical.
This is what our entrance looks like.
Without the signs for the birth and the emergency room.
Then you arrive at this door.
Often it is open, so when you arrive you can try to move a little in the door.
Is it open is it just to step in
And take the elevator up to plan 12. There we are.
In the evenings, nights and weekends, the door is locked.
Then there is a door phone you can call on
Then we let you in and you go up to level 12.
The blue arrow you see there will illustrate one of our parking lots
Just outside the entrance.
There you can stand for 30 minutes.
Then you need to move the car.
Or to the large parking lot at the southern entrance.
The red arrow points to the entrance that was in the picture before.
This is what it looks like when you come to plan 12 and into the department.
Unfortunately there are not always two happy midwives and wait
In the hall, when you come.
But at the frosted glass on the box, the coordinator has its small hold
And she usually sits in the booth.
Unless otherwise our expedition is just inside
And we always move around the entrance so we are aware of when you arrive.
When you come to us at birth, you are the focus.
All our work;
24 hours a day, 7 days a week, is about you.
About you as future parents and about the child.
You are the focus.
Around you are a whole team of professional people
where there are mainly midwives you will meet-
nurses.
We have many very good, experienced nurses-
With us, who gives you good advice and good support.
We have a very professional medical group with us as well.
It is not always possible to see a doctor when giving birth.
Sometimes you meet one or two midwives, no doctor.
It is perfectly normal.
Sometimes a doctor needs to be switched on
To discuss how your childbirth progresses.
There's don't have to be any dangerous or 'danger and travel'
Without that, we work in the team at BB Linköping.
Since we are a university hospital, we often have students with us.
Then it is mainly midwife students but also prospective doctors.
These midwife students are all nurses at the bottom
And have usually worked for at least one year in healthcare.
Often longer than that.
We can really strike a blow to have midwife students with them.
There will be another aspect in the whole
And another person who is there just for you, during childbirth.
However, it is always a responsible midwife who makes a decision, together with you.
The medical decisions are made by doctors and midwives.
Not by students.
There are many around you even if they are not visible in the hall, but in the background.
The medical candidates with us go their last semester
before they go out into the actual professional life.
So there are also experienced, future colleagues, you meet.
But of course it is always voluntary.
You have to choose whether you want to bring a student with you or not.
But we can recommend it.
In the picture we have a doctor and four midwives.
Sometimes it may be that the birth stops.
Maybe the child has set a little different in the pelvis.
It may be a reason why we need to discuss
How we can move on, how does this child stand.
That we need to share each other's advice, tips and our skills.
This is nothing secret for you
But sometimes it gets a little easier for us to go out of the hall and talk to each other-
then to come in to you and give the suggestion-
How can we continue to work during childbirth.
But as I said: all the time we work together in the department.
Although it is a midwife and a nurse
that is responsible for your birth-
are we all involved in all births-
And in several decisions as well.
We will go ahead and talk about how we work at childbirth.
On each workout there is a coordinator.
The coordinator is a used midwife who has a supervisory role.
One of her main tasks is to answer the phone when you call.
Telephone counseling is a big part of her job.
She has a coordinating feature
and distributes the women who are going to feed-
on the midwives who work on the passport, and the nurses.
Then we collaborate with a number of other clinics.
First and foremost, the neonatal department right next to the delivery department.
So we have both physically close there but also a close collaboration with Neo.
It could be a baby as one even before the birth
Know will need to be observed or cared for at NEO after childbirth.
But there may also be children who after childbirth
showing signs that they need some extra care-
or observed, a few hours or day on neo.
In addition to Neo, we cooperate a lot with the anesthetists.
Partly it is those responsible for pain relief or anesthesia
If it would be such as man-
For some reason needs surgery during or after their birth.
It is also those who put back anesthesia if you want it when you are going to give birth to your child.
We want you to know that they always do their utmost
to get as fast as possible but sometimes they are busy-
on surgery, IVA or the emergency room.
Then it may take before they arrive.
But their goal is to get as fast as possible.
We also collaborate with other hospitals, mainly the Vrinevis Hospital in Norrköping.
It may be that we are full of us or for some reason
Can't receive you, when you call the birth.
Then we sometimes need to refer to another hospital.
In the first place, it is Norrköping we refer to because it is closest.
Those in Norrköping have access to your medical records, just like us.
They can read about how your pregnancy has been and if you made any wishes there.
When we refer there, we do it for you.
In order for you to receive the best possible care.
That there should be a midwife, nurse and doctor
Who has the opportunity to receive you and give you support when giving birth to your child.
We know that there is a concern many people carry with them before childbirth.
A concern about being referred to another hospital.
It's not often, but it happens.
And it will be good anyway.
Collaborates we also do with women's health
when it comes to controls and such during your pregnancy.
Education, it says.
We attend continuous education, we who work as midwives,
Nurses and doctors in the team that Lina talked about.
We have exercises where we train together
in situations that do not arise so often-
But as we need to be good at, be able to act fast, once it happens.
There we have continuous exercises and training situations.
Maybe you want to give some examples of some exercises we have
We train partly on seat deliveries, for example.
It is not very common but it sometimes happens.
Then we get to practice dolls, pelvis and
The various handles used in a seat delivery.
Same with suction clock.
We also train that.
And children's exercises, where we practice taking care of children who
Not so good at childbirth.
That needs a little extra-
Breathing support, for example, when they come out.
As Lina said before we are a university hospital
Which means that it is conducted, more or less, always research there.
It may be that you, during your stay, be asked if you want to participate in a study.
You may have already received that question from women's health
And are included in a study already when you come to us.
This is obviously voluntary.
Then you change the coordinator on the three shift.
Many times when you call us you get to talk to the same person.
We feel that you often think it is a security.
You first call maybe eight in the morning and then Sofia answers on the phone
When you call next time at ten o'clock, Sofia will also answer.
Then you don't have to pull your entire story once again
Without knowing that you are there and what you have talked about before.
Of course, you always record what the discussion has been about.
It may feel a little nice for you to hear the same voice.
It is our experience and the feedback we usually get.
When to call the birth
You should call when you suspect that the birth has started.
For example through pain, if the water has gone or
If you get a bleeding.
Or if you feel insecure about these aspects.
Sometimes, when you expect your first child, it's not always easy to know,
How is it when the water goes
You have not been involved before.
You don't really know how much water it will come.
Or how much is a bleeding
Is it a little pink on the toilet paper or as a menstrual bleeding
Then you call and balls with us.
If one has questions one does not consider as emergency
Without thinking it could wait a bit ...
We understand that it is difficult to decide for you who are sitting there at home
The phone number you see here: Feel free to put it in your phones
So that you have it available.
Preparation for childbirth.
How can you prepare for you to give birth to children,
No matter what child in the order it is
We have lined up some different circles about how to do
In order to feel mentally and perhaps physically report-
Before the upcoming birth.
What we think is the most important thing is what is the greatest highlighted:
The parent support we offer you here and now.
Just by listening to Caroline and me today
Have you come a pretty good bit on the "birth preparation road".
However, you should not feel that you must know this.
That it is a test, an exam, you should go through.
This is some advice and support.
That there is little in mind about how a birth can go.
A little what might be good to know.
But you should not split up that this is exactly how it will be.
That this is how I should have it
Without having a thought about "How would I wish it will be?"-
but still have an open mind-
About that it may not be exactly as I expected.
It might be something else.
But it can also be good.
Positive role models, we have also written.
When you are pregnant you often get a lot of stories from loved ones,
workmates and neighbor.
They would like to tell you what it was like when they were going to give birth to children.
Try to sell a little there.
Is it that you get "horror stories"
Is it totally okay to say: No thanks!
I'm not so interested in listening.
It makes me scared, or worried.
Collect your great experiences instead.
It strengthens you more than listening to
The single, scary and dramatic stories.
What to bring with you for childbirth.
We will talk a little about food and drink
And such things.
Caroline will go into it.
And the most basic stuff will be there.
Binds to mom, diapers for baby, towel, panties to mom
And night shirt.
It will be there, the most basic.
You can give birth to children without even having a bag, believe me.
Physical preparation.
What can you do then
You really have to live based on what you feel good about.
Are you a woman who feels good about exercising, run several workouts a week
And feel both physically and mentally good about exercising, then you should do it.
Are you the type that is not so physically active
Do you continue to live as you always do.
For example, pregnancy yoga or water gym for pregnant women.
If you want to do that, it is great, but do what you feel good about.
You will pass this birth
Even if you have not trained four workouts per week during pregnancy.
You have that ability anyway.
The mental preparation.
Allow yourself to go down in turns during the end of pregnancy.
This is totally okay not to “drive on” in life
With 110 percent beer all the time until the day you are going to give birth to children.
"Boa" a little at home.
Maybe prepare some food boxes, bed the baby bed ...
And mainly use materials written by the profession.
There are very nice and good books
Which is written by midwives, and for which we can strike a blow.
If we move on, there is also at 1177,
The care guide, a lot of information about pregnancy and childbirth,
Which we can really hit a blow for, so use it.
What happens then when you come in to us at the birth
Whatever you are looking for, if you get into a check
or if the painters have started, or the water gone-
and one has come into an active birth work-
We almost always start taking blood pressure, urine tests and weight.
Just as you have done on women's health during pregnancy
And for the same reason.
Then we also want to switch on a CTG,
a fetal monitoring to see how the baby has it in the stomach
And also how much contractions come.
In the top, a little choppy, curve of the picture you see the baby's heart sound.
The lower, black, with tops and valleys
are contractions that come, disappear and come again.
This is what it looks like when you connect the curve.
The lower box records the baby's heart sound
And the upper detects when the uterus becomes hard.
Then there will be a pressure against the box that is recorded as
A "bun" on the screen.
We attach them with elastic bands.
The boxes are often allowed to lie with a little while
Or walk around a bit in the room.
Sitting up usually works too.
But that we get a good first registration of the baby.
They last for about 2030 minutes so we can judge how the baby is doing.
Is it difficult to get in touch with the child, if you want to wander around the room
Maybe we need to ask you to be in bed for the first 20-30 minutes.
It is important to point out about surveillance, CTG as it is called
That sometimes we slip a little and say that we should "run a curve".
This means that you do a CTG monitoring on the child.
It is our responsibility, not yours.
That responsibility we take
Even when we midwives are not with you, we see this surveillance
At different parts of the birth, so that is our responsibility.
It can be a little blood, a little brownish fresh blood coming.
Once we have done the vaginal examination, known on the uterus,
And together with the other parameters: how you feel, by the way,
How your controls are located, how much pain you have,
How you feel, how you handle the painters we make an assessment.
Partly where you are in your childbirth work
But also if the best for you is to get help with some pain relief-
And go home again.
Or if you are going to stay, and give birth to children.
It is not entirely unusual, when waiting for your first child
that you get into a check and have to go home again.
The birth has not really started but it is difficult to decide for yourself
And it's hard to decide for us, on the phone, too.
Don't see it as a defeat.
The first child is very common.
Your time is coming.
When you will remain at birth.
The latency phase, we will come in now.
It is the first part of the birth
Where the uterus is "mature".
It is shortened and it starts to open.
The latency stage can take time.
Like all stages during childbirth, each stage is very individual.
Some women do not know the latency stage very much.
They get a struck a established work fairly
with painful contractions that increase in strength,
While other women have a long latency spoon.
One day, several days.
Are we in the latency or active stage
It doesn't matter that much, because we don't always know either.
When it goes from one to the other.
What is important is how to manage the painters at home.
When you can't handle them at home anymore, you should be with us, if you want to.
Each birth takes time, and is unique.
It's nothing strange if the birth takes 24 hours
from the fact that the painters start, until the baby is out-
When you expect your first child.
Just as Caroline said: Patience, Patience, Patience ...
Allow yourself to set aside this time for childbirth.
Don't stress it.
It must take time.
That's how it is, physiological.
When you are in the latency stage, it can of course be difficult to determine;
Am I in it or not?, at least am the primary rest.
You can't, like Caroline, said "go" a birth.
It is hormones that control not activity.
But as the birth progresses and the painters become denser, denser
and more and more painful one can expect to
that the birth has entered an active stage.
Then there is little difference.
Then it is good to try to get up.
To be in an upright position from time to time.
To try to move, in a different way.
Many times, at this stage, you are with us at the birth.
Then we can give you support, advice and tips.
Sometimes, even, we have to "whip" you to be more active.
Some women think it is very nice to be able to lie down in bed all the time
And you can do that.
As long as the birth is moving forward.
But many times you need to be in a little more movement.
We will look at some pictures based on slightly different positions.
We have a colleague who can illustrate it.
Here our colleague sits on a so -called "birth pallet".
When you sit on it you can have your partner,
Or his support person, behind him that you can lean on.
Then you are in an upright position.
The baby is given the opportunity to penetrate the pelvis,
Press the cervix so that it opens more easily.
If you sit then you often have partners close, giving love and closeness
which also releases oxytocin, "vicinity"- and "feed the child hormone"-
Which gives you many times more effective pain.
You can try it.
Some think it is a bit wobbly in the beginning when you sit on it.
Then we, or partner, can sit on a chair behind
and hold the hips, to stabilize a little at first-
so that one does not sit and tense —
Without trying to sit with the shoulders far down and be as relaxed as you can in the pelvis.
Feel free to roll with your hips while sitting on the ball.
This is not something you need to remember.
We will help, guide and show you when you are with us.
In the next picture we have a "walking table".
It is usually very popular.
Many who want to stand, think it is nice to have something to rest against.
As you can see, our colleague is steadily standing with both feet in the floor.
Many times when one gets hurt, in other situations in life
If you want to stand on your toes.
One spans the buttocks,
the abdomen and the whole body.
If you stand with your feet firmly in the floor, you will not be excited.
Feel free
And wiggle your hips even there, just like when sitting on the ball.
Here you can also give birth to children.
Standing.
If the baby is doing well, and you are doing well, you can stand up and feed.
There is no problem whatsoever.
But we show, and we help you, to vary position.
You might start with one, then you take the next ...
... then you go back to the ball.
You can hold on for hours, change position.
Then of course you have to rest as well.
You are not bad because you lie down in bed from time to time.
It should, and can definitely do.
We help you, and alternating positions we think can suit you best.
Then we have a picture of a delivery room.
Here we have canceled all the different tools;
Ball, walking table, delivery pallet, sacco bag.
In the background you see the door to the bathroom.
We have sitting baths in most of our rooms.
This is what a delivery room looks like.
In all rooms there is a shower, even where there is no bathtub.
Possibility of heat and water is available in all rooms.
Breathing and relaxation.
Just like being active during childbirth
The relaxation is also very important.
That you try to relax between the painters.
You will have more breaks than pain during the entire delivery process.
It can be good to have it as a small mantra.
That when it is tough, think:
"I soon have a break, it is longer than the pain".
That you try to allow yourself to rest.
You may need some support and help from your partner in it:
Now is the break.
We try to fold down the shoulders.
Exhale the last evil
Cut your eyes.
And go down in turns between the painters.
All this is easier said than done.
But that you try not to be:
"Now there is a pain ... and it will do a huge pain ...".
That one is not up in turns in between but allows yourself to go down
between the painters.
We help you with that.
To breathe during childbirth.
We do breathe, whether we want to or not.
Many times you hear: Breathe breath!
Breathe...
But it's a bit about how to breathe.
In the 70s, when I was born, my mother attended a psychoprophylaxis course.
Then they were told to breathe right in the right way during childbirth
Will you feed painlessly.
As a result, quite a few women in the 70s felt unsuccessful.
They felt that: "It did really well, then I must have breathed wrong".
Really we don't say now.
However, breathing is a good tool during childbirth.
To try to breathe with long, deep breaths
in through the nose, out through the mouth.
To try to relax even when it hurts.
Feel free to try it at home.
There is an endless amount of different
respiratory courses and yoga courses and “Five without fear”-
on the web, which you can take part in.
See if you find something that fits you-
As a tool to be able to face the pain during childbirth.
Partner Support & amp;
Strengthen, it says.
In the picture we see a woman who is in an active work
and with the help of his partner who both support and strengthen her-
Physically, but also by being there.
Maybe say these words you have trained together before
Help find back to that quiet breathing.
To help to see that now it is rest and not pain.
That you have trained on these things together
Can be very useful during the course of childbirth.
As far as partners are concerned, many people come to us and do not know what they are expected to do.
One feels powerless that the one you love is in so hurt
and not be able to do anything to relieve.
But there is a lot you can do.
Partly by just being there, in the room.
Sit next to, hold a hand ...
... though not holding a hand when it doesn't fit.
It may be to give massage.
Touch and proximity release, as Lina said, oxytocin and makes
The woman's body can cause childbirth to move forward.
Massage can also mean a little less comfortable massage.
That you push in the back or hold pretty hard on the woman's hips
When the painters arrive.
It can mean very different things.
Maybe you put on the playlist that you have done during pregnancy.
Or produce the birth letter that you have written together.
Maybe during some parts of the birth for your woman's action a bit.
If these are questions you have been thinking about at home that she can't handle, or setting
Not just during the latency stage when you are at home trying to fill up
with energy and rest, but also during the active part of childbirth.
You have to think a little that it is like a marathon
As you both should perform in different ways, where you need energy.
We have everything with us at childbirth when it comes to the woman.
There is juice, juice, yogurt, smoothies and so on.
There is also food if you stay with us
At a stage where food is a good idea.
Often you are not so hungry for meat and potatoes when giving birth to children.
As a partner you need to bring what you want.
Snacks or maybe some food boxes.
Coffee and tea are with us.
It may change but we mention it so you don't
Bring ten food boxes, which you can throw when you come to us.
So there our family kitchen looks.
There is micro, fridge and such.
You may of course sit out here and eat if you want
But also bring your food box to your woman and be there.
Now we will quickly jump on to the end of the birth.
It starts at the penetration phase.
It is when the uterus has opened up
The more than ten centimeters.
Then the child's head should penetrate your pelvis.
It is the penetration phase, the final stage of childbirth.
Many times you can think that: Now it is open ten centimeters,
Now comes the child.
Now it's finished.
It's not always so.
Many times it may be a few hours left
To make the child penetrate your pelvis.
It is perfectly normal.
Especially when you are expecting your first child.
To get the child to penetrate, you can alternate positions.
The pictures contain a variety of positions you can be in, at this stage.
I will not tell you about every position.
Even there, at the birth, we will give you tips and advice.
These pictures also sit up in all the delivery rooms
With us at BB Linköping, so you can look, if you want it.
Do you have a strong desire to be in a special position when the child is born
Do you tell us.
Then we can help you get there-
At the last stage, when the child really is going out.
However, it is difficult to decide before exactly how you want it.
But if you have a thought and desire, then give it to us, we help you with it.
As long as you feel good and the child is doing well
Can you actually give birth in any position.
It is only the imagination that makes it.
There are infinitely many opportunities to give birth to their child.
The last part of the birth is the crime stage.
Some women may feel scared and worried about this last part
But what I want you to bring with you is also that many women-
Think it can be nice in a way.
During the opening phase and the penetration phase
Should you deal with every pain.
One should breathe, try to relax off-
And more receive what happens in the body.
In the coastal phase it becomes a bit in a different way.
You should suddenly start helping, pressing.
It can be experienced nicely.
You feel that things happen, that the baby is coming further and further down.
It is very different for different women,
How clearly the coastal stage is.
The pressure one feels at the end, that the child's head pushes down, under pain
Become more and more intense, more tangible.
Many times it goes into the fact that the woman feels she wants to
help press.
It becomes like a crystreflex-
which you can't control.
The body takes over a bit.
You can accompany the reflex.
Just as Lina has said, we are here with you.
You are not alone in the room at this stage,
When the baby is to give birth and the woman starts to cruise.
We are there to support and guide.
Then applies exactly the same as before during childbirth
That there is always a break after the painters, even in the crime.
It is important to find the rest there, upload for the next pain.
Perineal protection is there.
It is something we practice and keep on all women who are going to give birth.
We will use either a hot towel
Or a glove that we have filled with hot water.
Many times it is perceived as a little pain relief.
It may be a little easier to dare to press, to cruise
When you have something that resists.
Don't you like it,
You think it hurts, or is uncomfortable then you tell.
You may want to tell us a little about what perineal protection is
When giving birth to children there is a risk of getting bursts
Especially when the baby's head is to be born.
Then the midwife, with one hand over perineum, holds
The middle yard between the anus and the vagina.
And even a hand on the baby's head
To be able to feel what pressure the baby will-
And maybe be able to slow down a little if it goes a little too fast.
It is in the middle yard that the towel or hot glove is placed.
Another part of perineal protection is the communication in the final stage.
That the midwife has a clear communication with the one to give birth
And guides, even with her words, how the woman should handle the last painters.
To press a little gently (carefully) or may not push at all
Although that's the only thing you want to do in that stage-
So that the baby is born, just when the head comes.
Sometimes the head comes out first and then the pain ends.
Then you have to rest, wait for the next pain to come
And the baby is born.
It is no wonder if it is so.
What also happens in the last part, in the crown phase
is that the woman often cries, cries and thinks that nothing happens
One starts to wonder: do you see any of the head
Often we do not do it at the beginning of the coastal stage.
It takes a little while.
Partly to get the technology, how to print,
But also to dare to press and listen to the body.
But the longer we get in the spoon the more server the midwife
and the nurse the baby's head.
Then they are a little tricky.
The head slides back a bit between the painters.
There is a purpose for it.
It should go a little slow.
The tissue should be stretched.
It is not uncommon, when giving birth to your first child,
That it can take one to two hours to cruise.
It is perfectly normal.
It can go faster than that hour but also take longer.
Even in this situation, you may need to change position.
You might start to cruise in some position and feel that I don't get it.
I don't get any power when I lie like this, on the side.
You have to try it out, to the position you enjoy in well
and a position where the midwife has good supervision over your middle-yard-
and can help you in the best way.
Something we often get to us too
During both pregnancy and childbirth, when talking about this stage-
is that they are so afraid that stool will come.
It will.
It is the same muscles that control the cruising, in the vagina
Which also controls the cruising when going to the toilet and poop.
If you crawl with the vagina, you also crush with the tail.
Then there will be some stool.
We try not to do any big deal.
We wipe it away and throw it.
Try not to think so much about it.
It will come.
Rather, think it's good.
If there is a little stool, you crush correctly.
Then things happen too
The crazy thing you can do is to excite, to try to hold it.
Then the baby does not come down either.
Then you squeeze the baby as well.
Energy can also be a thing in this last stage.
You feel that I will not be able to cruise the child.
Often you have a long work work behind it.
One has run a large part of the "marathon",
Is on the rally and feels pretty end.
We know, from experience, that you can cope.
In some strange way, both the woman and the partner get,
or the relative who is with, energy at the end
Because you know the baby is soon here.
Even then we will help.
Take some juice, a little dextrosol, some juice or whatever it might be
So that you can cope with the last bit.
You as a partner are very important even at this stage.
That you are with your woman in this and pepper her.
That you can cope with this last bit even if you are very tired yourself.
You lift her by saying she's strong,
That she is the best.
That she can handle this.
You don't help her as much if you say that
You understand that she is very tired, how should you be able to cope?
I see that you are tired.
Try to turn it around instead, to “Now we're at the end”,
That she can cope, that she can, that you do this together.
That you will soon be able to meet your baby.
Lift her in this
Very important.
After the birth of the child there will happen some things in the room
which we midwives and nurses do.
You may not notice some of the stuff that happens.
You get the baby up on your chest or stomach
And often has full focus on the little creature.
We have as a routine to take samples in the umbilical cord when the baby is newborn.
The samples can give us important information
If it is a baby that is a bit taken when it comes out,
Which doesn't really get started screaming and breathing as we wish.
Then the samples tell us how the baby has had
The last time in the stomach, during childbirth.
It can help us interpret a little
Why the baby doesn't really feel as we wish.
It also stands.
We always practice late naveling,
which means we let the umbilical cord pulse fully
If you feel that you do not want, it is totally okay.
Or if the woman wants to cut it herself it goes great.
Otherwise we do.
Many times it becomes so that the placenta is born
Before we cut the umbilical cord.
Then we cut the umbilical cord afterwards.
Rupture and suturing.
As we mentioned before, this with perineal protection
If you often break, you get a rupture when giving birth,
Above all, his first child.
Then it is very common.
We are good at looking for ruptures.
We investigate very carefully afterwards.
Of course one gets anesthesia as a woman
Before we have to investigate-
Is it very important to have the baby close, skin against skin.
When they are newborn, there is a lot to learn just when they come out.
They should learn to breathe themselves, keep their blood sugar
And learn to keep warm so that they do not sink in temperature.
And skin against skin promotes this process
Both in terms of breathing, temp and blood sugar.
It also promotes breastfeeding in a very good way.
Is it that you have planned to breastfeed your child
so it might be desirable to get to a first breastfeed-
Sometime during the first hours after childbirth.
That the baby may be at the chest.
Look and lick,
Eventually get a while.
And start sucking.
Often the babies are spiked for the first few hours after childbirth
then to get a little tired and want to sleep-
Almost most of the first 24 hours.
Not without exception.
There are always spike babies who do not want to sleep.
But the idea is that you should get a little break and be able to recover.
Skin against skin: it must not be the mother child lies with
There are reasons why the child cannot be with the mother
can it always lie skin to skin of the other parent-
in such cases.
It also goes great.
Or with the person who is present during childbirth, of course.
Here is a picture of a father who cuts the umbilical cord.
Then comes a target image.
"Congratulations" you get
When the birth is over, the placenta is out-
And a possible rupture is sutured.
You should land, enjoy and get in your energy.
We move on to some other situations at the birth,
that has nothing to do with the birth.
For example, water discharge.
Sometime during childbirth or pregnancy, the water will go.
For some, the water goes far too early in pregnancy.
For some, it is a start to childbirth.
For some, the water goes during childbirth
and for some do not go the water all-
Without the child is born throughout the membranes.
Once the child comes out, take holes in the membranes.
It is very unusual, but it happens.
If the water goes when you are at home, we want you to call us.
It is about half a liter of water you have
And new water is formed all the time.
So when the water has gone-
Will it continue to run.
It never gets dry in there.
New water is constantly formed.
We understand that one can be a little unsure whether the water has gone or not,
But many times when the water goes you notice it.
It flows along the legs and often becomes a pool on the floor.
It is so much water.
Imagine you would pour out half a liter of fluid on the floor,
Then you see it.
Of course, there are exceptions.
Do you feel uncertain about it, or when you think the water has gone
How to call us.
We set different control questions-
Setting the delivery painting is soon after that.
Not always, but quite often.
Is it then to get into a check
At once after the water has gone, you come to us,
Make a check and have to go home again.
Just until you get home, the painters may start.
Then you have to go in again.
Therefore, we will say that you can wait up to 14 hours.
You will have a time to get to us on a check.
We check how you and the child feel.
Is it that the water would be discolored in some way,
It is something you do with you on maternity care with you.
Some women need to come on an extra visit
To us at the birth, and you get to see a doctor.
It is a so-called "week 41 control"-
where you assess when you can start the birth-
And sometimes you can judge how to start it.
But it is very individual.
One is allowed to start from
How it's just for you.
When it is mode.
We have start -ups at birth every day.
What we want to send with you if it is so that you get started
is to be patient there too.
Expect several days with us.
What also becomes, at a start is that the entire latency phase
happens with us at the birth instead of at home,
Where you might shower and bathe, wander around a bit and eat and drink.
You can do that with us instead.
And then it can be experienced even longer than if you had been home.
Turning the child.
Sometimes you have a small kid who chooses to lie down with the tail down
instead of with your head down.
Then you are offered a turn-
Around week 35, 36.
Then you start by making an ultrasound to see that the child is normal sized
And that the placenta has the features it needs.
Do you see that everything looks normal you have to come to us a definite day
And you try to get the child to turn.
Then you start with a CTG monitoring, which we talked about before.
You get a cannula in the arm, with drugs that make you relax.
When done, a doctor will try to get the child to
do like a small volt.
From outside, on your stomach, have their hands-
And get the child to turn.
From the tail, to the head down.
It should not hurt
But it is clear that it is uncomfortable when you are there and "provokes".
What many women think is very uncomfortable
is that you "pull against the skin" on you, on your stomach.
But it is you who controls.
If you say stop, now I need a break.
The times we do not succeed you have two options.
To give birth to his child with planned Caesarean section
Or to give birth to his child in the seat.
Then you also have to make an ultrasound to check the size of the child.
One also makes a pelvic X -ray on you
To see that you have enough pelvic-
To be able to raise this child.
If you meet these criteria and then get started in pain work,
That you do not get started, there are no increased risks in giving birth to a child in the seat.
However, one should feel safe with it, as a birth.
It is very important.
But we have good experience of seating.
Otherwise, we would not have offered it with us.
So you can do that, in such cases.
Otherwise, it will be a planned caesarean section.
In Östergötland, all planned caesarean sections are carried out in Norrköping.
We must go into deviating birth process.
Suction clock, it stands at the top.
Surely most people have heard of this.
It can feel a little scary.
Many women, and partners, express a certain fear of suction clock.
In some cases a suction clock is needed, it is an aid we can take to
to help the baby to be born.
We see a suction clock in the picture.
It's like a small suction.
One creates a vacuum using a small device
that is rolled into the room.
You attach the cup to the baby's head.
In order to use a suction clock, the cervix needs to be completely open.
The baby needs to have come down the last bit in the birth canal
And have set up, in a good way.
It is also the case that the woman needs to help cruise.
It's not just that we come and pull out the baby.
When the woman has a pain, she cries just as before.
A doctor helps with the suction clock,
Pulls it, and helps the baby a little further.
The reason why a suction clock may be needed
may be that the uterus who worked for many, many hours-
starting to get tired, the woman is tired, the painters are not that effective-
Then you may need to help with a suction clock.
It may also be that the baby signals
With the help of the CTG with which we monitor the child, and interpret,
or with the help of blood tests that we can take from the baby's head
That it feels bad in the stomach and needs to come out.
We then judge that the mother cannot cruise the child
As fast as the child needs to be born, you can take the help of a suction clock.
Of course, you get information in the meantime, and before this.
We talk about it afterwards too.
But important to know is that the woman is active in this process,
Am himself with and crawl out his child.
Many times you can help the baby down, almost all the way out.
Then you can let go of the clock and the mother is allowed to cruise the child the last bit.
Good to know is that there is always an extra midwife in the room
In this situation, and maybe more staff otherwise.
Maybe a nurse.
So there may be some more people in the room
Just when putting the suction clock.
As we said earlier we always call
to the neonatal staff, a pediatrician, nurse and nurse.
Staff from Neo are always in our children's room nearby
If they had to help the baby a little.
Something else about suction clock
No.
I think you got what we want.
Sphincter rupture.
An Sphincter rupture means that the woman has received a
that engages someone, or both, of the rectum muscles, the Sfinktrar-
As we have, around the rectum.
There is an external sphincter that we call external sphincter.
Then there is an internal, internal, sphincter muscle.
When giving birth to children and gets a greater rupture
Could it be that either, or both, these muscles break.
Partly, or completely, when you give birth to children.
Should it occur, it is a doctor who sews the ruptures.
It is done on surgery.
Often the woman is anesthetized for a while or gets some kind of pain relief
And maybe get a little sedated, so this should be manageable for you.
The good thing about sewing the ruptures and that they are sewn on surgery
is that there are better conditions for the person who is going to sew the rupture.
Good lighting, and operating staff who can help.
And better opportunity for pain relief and anesthesia for you.
Have you received a greater rupture when giving birth to children
You are followed up more carefully even after childbirth.
Of course, you get information at the birth and BB.
Both in writing and orally.
You will also be followed during the first year after childbirth
To see how the rupture heals and how you feel.
Bleeding.
All women who give birth to children bleed, more or less.
Up to a liter we think is a normal bleeding.
It does not mean that we are waiting until it has soaked a liter.
Notices the midwife that it bleeds on a little
There are different things we do to try to stop the bleeding.
A liter of extra blood approximately, based on how big one is,
you gather during pregnancy to be able to ha-
Reserves to be able to bleed when giving birth to children.
If one suffers a large bleeding,
it may siva at a slow pace but if it eventually becomes a larger amount
Are there drugs we can give.
We also need to squeeze and press your uterus,
Feel that it contracts properly after childbirth.
More people can also come into the room and help.
They give drugs and squeeze on the stomach.
In some cases, the woman is bleeding very and fast after childbirth.
Then there are always a lot of people in the room.
In such situations we have no opportunity to inform you there and then
What happens and what we do.
It is such a situation that we talked about earlier,
It may be that the placenta does not come off.
We get into it, that the placenta does not release
And that the uterus then cannot contract properly.
There may be other reasons why the uterus is not really
Man can contract after childbirth.
It may be a rupture you have received, a vessel that has broken, which bleeds.
It can be difficult to stop.
When the placenta does not loosen:
What we do to get it out is to help with oxytocin,
The hormone one has had full of in the body during childbirth
And still rushing around the body when giving birth to children.
But you may need some extra oxytocin to help the placenta to release,
And the uterus to contract, to reduce the risk of a large bleeding.
Is it that it is difficult to get out the placenta
Do we have some tips and tricks to add.
One can gently pull a little in the umbilical cord
And hold over your stomach to lead out the placenta.
But does not work it you need to go to surgery
Once you have taken a sample of the baby and seen that it
Shows signs of a little oxygen deficiency in the last stage of childbirth.
Then we can take the help of a suction clock for the baby to be born a little faster.
Then we always take the help of the neo staff who are in place.
What happens inside the hall is that the one who has been your responsible midwife
During childbirth always stays with the woman who has given birth, inside the hall.
There will be another midwife and helps the baby out
to a "children's table", children's room, which we have with us at birth.
There will be a picture here on the child's table itself
With all the equipment around.
The staff is from the neonatal department.
Neo, as I said, is wall to wall with us.
They are quickly in place about a baby
Need some extra support and care after childbirth.
We would like partners or relatives to accompany the baby out
And is with the baby at the children's table while staff stay with the mother.
Many times when you need to take the baby out to the team that stands waiting for
Will the baby return to the birth mother pretty soon.
Only everything has stabilized.
It is by far the most common.
Sometimes they already scream on the way out but one may still want to go out
There are other birth proceedings as well
which abandon the most common, the most normal.
Settlement.
I went into it a bit before.
That one must "qualify" in order to give birth to your child in the seat.
Have you done that, and meet all the criteria we talked about before
Can you give birth to your child in the seat.
Once you get started in a birth work
must the birth proceed normally all the time,
Because you can't put a suction clock on a seat.
You can only put a suction clock on a head, not on a tail.
The birth must move forward as we expect, all the time.
When it's time to give birth, when one starts to cruise
Will there be some more people in the hall.
Just like what we talked about before, when putting a suction clock
So we call some extra staff.
It is always a doctor with, and an extra midwife.
Possibly an extra nurse.
But we try to keep the environment calm and sensed
So that it should be as calm and safe for you as we can.
But a little more staff is required.
It is the same in twin delivery.
In case of triple loss, when waiting for three children
You give birth with the help of Caesarean section.
It is not possible to keep track of all three, during a work work.
Who has these heart sounds and who has these?
And these?
We believe that it is safer to give birth to Caesarean section.
Twin delivery, where you can give birth vaginally.
A little depending on how the children are placed in the stomach.
Whether they lie with head or tail downwards, or across.
It is an individual assessment with the help of ultrasound and maternal care.
But even there, when the children are to come out and one starts to cruise
there will be more people inside the hall, such as at a suction clock or seat.
Sometimes the birth must be terminated with the help of Caesarean section.
It is for the reasons that Caroline talked about,
With suction clock.
Either it is that mom or child is not feeling well
Or that the birth does not go forward.
It has stalled.
The caesarean sections do not take place at the birth.
They take place in the operating department, which is wall to wall with us.
It is quick to move over there.
When you get there, there is a lot of staff there too.
It is one, or usually two, obstetricians, midwives,
nurse from the birth, pediatrician team
and the entire operation team with operating nurses,
Anesthetist, anesthesia nurses.
So there are a lot of people in there.
You should not be afraid of that.
It is a security.
Everyone has their own specific, extremely important, tasks.
The tasks are to make it safe, safe and good for you.
You should not hux flux give birth to children at ICA Maxi's parking.
It wouldn't have been good for her mother or baby.
This shows to us that something important is happening.
The pain;
It is important that you think that it is not dangerous.
It will not hurt you or your baby, but it is there.
What we can do is relieve the pain but we can't remove it
Or the fact that you feel something is happening in your body.
That it presses, sore or molar.
Although there is much we can do to relieve.
It is important to know, as Lina has said before,
That there is always a break, and it will be longer than the pain.
When you have the worst, you know that soon the pain with you.
There will be a break.
Trying to find, and "catch", the break we will help you with.
And catch you back in the rest between the painters.
The painting pain is a transient pain.
It goes over when the baby is out.
Then you can be tender and tired
But the very pain of the body working,
and the delivery pain from pain disappears when the baby comes out
Pain relief, as I said.
There are things we can do to relieve the pain
And as you can do at home.
Tactile massage we have talked a little about, touch and release of hormones.
It may be the pressure on the hips that we talked about
Which can feel nice in some stages of childbirth.
Tens, it says.
You have probably heard of that.
It is a tool one can use in other pain conditions,
Not just when giving birth to children.
It stands for "Transutan electrical nerve stimulation".
This device can advantageously be used if you have pain especially in the back.
Far down in the lumbar spine.
We do not recommend that you put the plates on your stomach
Without using them on their backs.
For those of you who don't know, a tendon is connected to two tiles-
As you attach where the pain is located.
Then the "nerve stimulation" is sent that blocks the brain's pain receptors.
It can have a pain -relieving effect.
Tens can work best in the latency stage
or at the beginning of the active stage in childbirth.
We have a tendon with us that you are very happy to borrow-
If you are interested in this.
It can be a little tricky if you
Never seen a TENS apparatus before, to get the technology.
Are you a little interested in tens, or have tried it before
and seemed to have worked well-
So we recommend that you rent an apparatus during pregnancy-
So that you can look and fiddle a little with it before.
And also have the opportunity to use it in the latency stage,
If you are at home at that stage, to get the greatest effect of it.
Sterile quads are a somewhat disputed pain relief method.
Some women think it works great.
And some women cannot imagine
How to want more pain when you already have pain.
It hurts quite to get the sterile quad.
This means that you inject some sterile water
Just below the skin, where you have the most pain.
It can be on the back, stomach or down towards the groin;
A pain that does not really let go of between the painters.
Then it can work well with sterile quads.
We are usually two midwives who put these at the same time
And we do it when the woman has a pain.
Often in four places, we inject some water.
This can work great a few hours
Then you may need to fill up, because the body absorbs the sterile water.
We have talked about warmth, and shower and bath.
Curaax, it says.
and get information about how you can go about
To rent a pool.
That's what one can do,
Rent a pool and take us with us.
Then we more than happy at the birth itself
in water, if you wish.
There are also some criteria we want you to fulfill
For it to be judged to be safe with a delivery in water.
You will also talk about that, with your midwife.
Then we move on, to the medical pain relief.
The foundation can be paracetamol, ie Panodil, or Alvedon.
As Caroline talked about before
It is great to use at home, so very much like it.
When you come to us and notice that
Now this type of pain relief does not help anymore,
The non -medical that Caroline talked about.
Or with panodil, one feels this is doing too bad
And I want something more that can relieve.
Then you can, for example, start with a tablet called Citodon.
It's like a mixture between paracetamol, panodil
And a slightly lighter morphine preparation can be said.
It is completely harmless if one takes single doses
during pregnancy or childbirth.
Only one is absolutely no danger.
We have also started more and more with oxynorm
Like pain relief in the early stage, the latency stage.
So you can also encounter it if you get into latency phase
and need some pain relief, that you get a tablet-
which is a morphine tablet, fast -acting but short -acting.
It can help.
It usually works pretty well,
When you come in to us.
If one is in the latency stage
But it is so painful that one is unable to be at home-
It usually works quite well with citodon or morphine.
Either in tablet form or as a syringe.
If you want to get the syringe, you have to stay with us.
Then you can't go home again but be with us and sleep.
Nitrous oxide knows a lot of people.
It is a very common pain relief method.
I should not say that everyone uses it, because so it is not
But very many, during childbirth itself.
We will not just give you a nitrous oxide mask and say:
"Here you go".
We will tell you exactly how to do.
Another pain relief method used quite a lot,
Especially at firstborns here in Linköping
Is EDA, back anesthesia.
It is an anesthetic form that is very effective during the opening phase.
It is an anesthetist who builds it.
It goes so that you can sit on the bedside
Alternatively lie on the page.
The anesthetist washing his back sterile,
Gives local anesthesia first, in the skin.
Local anesthesia is like any other syringes, you feel when laid.
But it is a short -term pain, a stick in the back.
When it is laid, you insert a hose between two vertebrae.
This hose then gets connected to a small pump
which you attach to your patient shirt.
It is continuously pumped in pain relief drugs, as long as you need it.
Sometimes you need to fill the pump with a little extra
Pain relief, if you get a pain break.
It is important to think here too that it is pain -relieving drugs.
It doesn't remove everything.
You will above all feel
The pressure downwards, towards the vagina and tail, when the child is pressing down.
It is not possible to stun away with a back anesthesia.
Is it something you want to add?
-No.
Then there is something called PCB.
It is when you put a local anesthesia in the uterus itself.
One of our doctors puts it and then stunning
Instead of putting it in your mouth, put it in the mother.
It helps a couple of hours.
It can be good to use if one is a nursery
And you know that the birth is probably going faster this time.
You may not have time to get any effect from the back anesthesia.
Then this may be preferable in such cases.
Then there is PDB, pelvic floor anesthesia
Where you stuck the pelvic floor.
Pelvic floor, the slide opening could be said
And the middle yard, one stays.
There you have pain when you start cruising.
During the opening phase and the penetration phase
Is it more that you have stomach pain, back, hips, thighs and buttocks.
Then it is not in the vagina itself you are in pain.
In the final stage, that pain is coming.
Then one can stun the pelvic floor
using a syringe.
One puts a syringe on one side of the vagina,
Inside the vagina, and a syringe on the other side.
If you think this pain is absolutely unbearable
And painful, we help you with it.
Just like with everything we've talked about today
regarding pain relief, positions,
How to give birth to your child, so try not to decide so much here and now.
See this as a suggestion, that this can be.
And so we talk more about it when you come to us
And it's time to give birth to your child.
What we return to all the time is that you will have breaks
between your aches, and we will be able to talk to each other,
to communicate.
It is so important and we want it so much.
Our wish is for you to get such a good
childbirth experience that is possible to give you.
We must do everything to be able to satisfy your wishes.
We want to say thank you and this moment.
Welcome to come and give birth to us.
Maybe we'll see you, who knows
As last words, do you want to flag
Yes for our Instagram, "BBLINKOPING".
Feel free to go in there and have a look.